<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The renevving of certaine orders deuised by the speciall commandement of the Queenes Maiestie, for the reliefe and stay of the present dearth of graine within the realme in the yeere of our Lord 1586. Nowe to bee againe executed this present yere 1594. vpon like occasions as were seene the former yere. With an addition of some other particular orders for reformation of the great abuses in ale-houses and such like.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Privy Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22690</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9201</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100698</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836528</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836528</idno>
            <idno type="VID">806</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22690)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 806)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 529:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The renevving of certaine orders deuised by the speciall commandement of the Queenes Maiestie, for the reliefe and stay of the present dearth of graine within the realme in the yeere of our Lord 1586. Nowe to bee againe executed this present yere 1594. vpon like occasions as were seene the former yere. With an addition of some other particular orders for reformation of the great abuses in ale-houses and such like.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Privy Council.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Privy Council.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the deputies of Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1594.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A revision of the orders of 1587 (STC 9194).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Food supply --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hotels --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bars (Drinking establishments) --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Taverns (Inns) --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:806:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:806:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The renewing of certaine Orders deuiſed by the <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall commandement of the Queenes</hi> Maieſtie, for the reliefe and ſtay of <hi>the preſent dearth of Graine within the Realme: in the yeere of our Lord</hi> 1586.</p>
            <p>Nowe to bee againe executed this <hi>preſent yere</hi> 1594. <hi>vpon like</hi> occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as were ſeene the former yere. <hi>With an addition of ſome other particular orders for Reformation of the great abuſes in Ale-houſes and ſuch like.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jmprinted at London by the Deputies</hi> of Chriſtopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie. 1594.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:806:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:806:2"/>
            <head>The renewing of certaine Orders <hi>deuiſed by the ſpeciall commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the Queenes Maieſtie, for the reliefe and ſtay of the preſent dearth of Graine within the Realme.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Shiriffe and Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Peace ſhal imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately vpon the receipt of theſe orders,<note place="margin">That the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into ſundry partes to execute theſe orders.</note> aſſemble them ſelues together w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as much ſpeede as they poſſible may: And hauing conferred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt themſelues vpon the contents hereof, ſhall firſt for the better execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame, diuide themſelues into ſundry companies, and take amongeſt them into their charge by ſeuerall diuiſions all the Hundreds, Rapes, or Wapentakes of the ſaid Countie.</p>
            <p>Item, euery companie ſo allotted out,<note place="margin">To appoint ſundry Iuries to inquire of things hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter following.</note> ſhall forthwith direct their Precepts vnto the Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe to warne the high Conſtables, vnder Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables, and other the moſt honeſt and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall inhabitantes within the ſame Hundred, Rape, or Wapentake, to the number of xxxvi. perſons, moe or fewer, as the quantitie of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:806:3"/> Hundred, Rape, or Wapentake ſhal require, to appeare before them at a certaine place, and within as ſhort time after the receipt hereof as they conueniently may, &amp; vpon the apparance of the ſayde perſons, they ſhall diuide them into ſo many Iuries, as they ſhall thinke meete, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing inſtruction to the ſaid Shiriffe to returne as fewe of ſuch as be knowen great Farmours for Corne, or that haue ſtore of graine to ſell, as he can. And ſuch of the perſons ſo warned as ſhall not appeare, but make default being ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned, and not hauing any iuſt or reaſonable excuſe alowable by the Iuſtices, to be puniſhed therefore at the good diſcretions of the Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, both by Impriſonment and Fine, before whom they are to appeare.</p>
            <p>Item, they ſhall firſt declare to the parties appearing, the cauſe why they are ſent for, and therewith earneſtly charge them in the feare of God, to apply themſelues to the ſeruice where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they ſhall be now called, with al duetiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and diligence, and without any partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to any perſon, and then they ſhall giue them the othe following.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Iuries Othe.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Othe of the Iurors, with charge to enquire what number of perſons be in the houſes of them that haue ſtore of Coine.</note>YOu ſhall ſweare &amp;c. that you ſhall enquire, and make true and due ſearch and triall, what number of perſons euery houſholder that hath Corne in their Barnes, Stackes or other where, as well Iuſtices of the Peace as others whatſoeuer, within the Pariſh of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> haue in their houſes feeding, lying, and vpriſing, or otherwiſe to bee
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:806:3"/> fed: what number of Acres they haue certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bee ſowen this yeere with any manner of Graine: what bargaines they haue made with any perſon for any kinde of Graine to bee ſolde, by, or to them: to whome and by whom, and vpon what prices they haue made the ſame, and what quantitie of any manner of Graine, they, or any other haue in their Barnes, Grai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Loftes, Cellors, or Floores, or otherwiſe to be deliuered vnto them vpon any Bargaine.</p>
               <p>Item, what number of Badgers, Kidders,<note place="margin">For Bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Brog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers of Corne.</note> Broggers or Carriers of Corne inhabite with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſayde Pariſh, and whither they doe vſe to carie their Corne which they doe buy, &amp; where they doe vſually buy the ſame, and what their names bee, and howe long they haue vſed that trade, and by whoſe Licence, and to ſee the ſame Licences of what tenor they are of.</p>
               <p>Item, what number of Mault makers,<note place="margin">Mault ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, Bakers, and Brewers.</note> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, common Brewers or Ciplers dwel with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſayde Pariſh, and who they are by name, and howe long they haue vſed that trade, and howe much they bake or brewe in the weeke, and what other trade they haue whereby o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to liue.</p>
               <p>Item,<note place="margin">Buyers of Corne to ſel againe.</note> who within the ſayde Pariſh bee the great buyers of Corne, or doe vſe to buy, or haue bought any Corne or Graine to ſell againe, or haue ſolde it againe ſince Midſommer laſt.</p>
               <p>Item,<note place="margin">Buyers of Corne vpon the ground.</note> who within the ſame Pariſh buyeth or haue bought or ſolde any Graine vpon the grounde, of whome, and to whome hath the ſame bene bought or ſolde, and at what price, and to certifie vnto vs of the Premiſſes, and of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:806:4"/> euery part thereof, on the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> now next comming: And to euery part of theſe Articles you ſhall bring anſwere from point to point.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt ſuch as ſhall refuſe, to declare the trueth of the matters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirable.</note>And if any ſhall refuſe to declare the trueth, of, or, concerning the premiſſes, or of any part thereof, to any the Iurours aforeſayde, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſame for their better information: the Iurours ſhall bee informed that ſuch perſon vpon the information of the ſayd Iurour, ſhall bee conuented before the Iuſtices of the Peace of the ſayde Diuiſion, or any two of them, and ſharply rebuked, or if neede be, puniſhed for his contempt. And if the partie ſo called in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhall not declare the full trueth thereof to the ſayde Iuſtices, he ſhall be committed by the ſaid Iuſtices to the common Gaile as a perſon bound for his good behauiour, and ſo to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued without Baile, vntill he ſhall conforme himſelf therein, or otherwiſe at the diſcretions of the ſaid Iuſtices, he ſhall be bound in a good ſumme of money to make appearance before the Lords of her Maieſties priuie Counſell to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere vnto his contempt in that behalfe,<note place="margin">Parties of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before the Counſaile.</note> for further puniſhment and fine, for enſample of al ſuch diſobedient perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that haue Corne, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine howe they ſhall ſerue the markets with ſuch por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as they may ſpare.</note>That the ſaide Iuſtices of the Peace hauing receiued into their hands the verdict of the ſaid Iuries anſwering to euery poynt of their charge, ſhall call at certayne dayes by them to bee aſſigned, ſuch perſons before them of euery Pariſh, as vpon the preſentment ſo made ſhall appeare to haue Corne to ſpare, and vpon due conſideration of the number of perſons,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:806:4"/> which euery perſon hath in his houſe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their qualities, and of the quantitie of Graine, that the partie hath towarde the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the ſame, or otherwiſe to be ſpent in his houſe and ſowing of his groundes, allowing to euery Houſeholder for his expenſes in his houſe, for euery perſon thereof according to their qualitie, ſufficient Corne for bread and drinke betweene this and the next Harueſt, and for their ſeede after the rate of the ſowing of that Countrey vpon an Acre. And then they ſhall binde all ſuch as ſhall appeare to haue more of any kinde of Graine, then ſhall ſerue to the vſes aboue mentioned, aſwell Iuſtices of the Peace as others, by Recognizance, in ſome good reaſonable ſome of money, to obſerue the orders enſuing, viz.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Ye doe knowledge your ſelfe to owe vnto our Soueraigne La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die the Queenes Maieſtie,<note place="margin">The forme of the Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance to be freely taken.</note> &amp;c. the ſumme of &amp;c.</head>
               <p>THe condition thereof ſhalbe, that if ye ſhall well and truely without fraud, couine, or colluſion, and without any maner deceite or craft fulfill, obſerue and keepe, all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſuch orders, appointments and directions, as ſhall at this preſent bee by vs on her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties behalfe preſcribed and enioyned vnto you to be by you done and fulfilled: Then this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognizance to be void, or els to ſtand in force.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:806:5"/>
               <head>The orders to be obſerued, are theſe, viz.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Orders to be obſerued by ſuch as ſhall be appointed to ſerue the Markets with Corne for the reliefe of the poore people firſt.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OU ſhall bring, or cauſe to bee brought weekly ſo many quarters or buſhels of corne, as Wheat, Rye, Barley, Mault, Peazon, Beanes, or other Graine, or ſo much thereof as ſhall not bee directly ſold to the poore Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers or day Labourers of the Pariſh within which you dwell, by order of the Iuſtices of the Peace of the Diuiſion within which you dwel, or two of them to the Market of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> there to be by you, or at your aſſignement ſolde vnto the Queenes ſubiects in open Market by halfe Quarters, two Buſhels, one Buſhell or leſſe, as the buyer ſhal require of you, and not in greater quantitie, except it be to a Badger or Carrier of Corne admitted according to the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute,<note place="margin">To whome Corne ſhall be ſold after that the poore are ſerued.</note> or to a common knowen Brewer or Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, hauing teſtimonie vnder the hand and ſeale of ſuch two Iuſtices of the Peace at the leaſt of the diuiſion, or of a Maior or other head Officer of the City, Towne, or Borough corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate where hee dwelleth, that hee is common Brewer or Baker within the ſame: or to ſuch other perſon as ſhall make prouiſion for any Lord Spirituall or Temporall, Knight, or any other Gentleman that hath no prouiſion of Corne, ſo as the ſame perſon haue and ſhew vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch perſon as ſhall haue the ouerſight of the Market in that behalfe, teſtimonie vnder the hand and ſeale of the partie for whom hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the Market to make that prouiſion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:806:5"/> that it is for the prouiſion of his houſe, and contayning the quantities and kinde of Graine to bee prouided: And you ſhall not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly leaue any part of your Corne ſo brought to that Market vnſolde, if money bee offered to you for the ſame, by any that are permitted to buy the ſame, after the vſuall price of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket there that day, as long as the Market ſhal laſt.</p>
               <p>Neither ſhal you from the beginning of the Market, to the full ende thereof,<note place="margin">No Corne brought to the Market vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolde, to bee ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out of the towne.</note> keepe or cauſe to be kept any of your ſaid Corne out of the ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſight of the Market: neither ſhall you carry away from the Market Towne any kinde of Graine that was brought thither which you haue not there ſolde, but ſhall leaue the ſame there in the Market Towne in ſome place knowen, ſo as it may be brought into the open Market the next Market day at the firſt ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Market, there to bee ſolde as afore was limitted. And yet neuertheleſſe, you ſhall bring to the Market ſuch other quantitie of Graine as ſhall be limitted, and ſo continue at euery Market day the bringing into the open Market, the quantitie of Corne that ſhall be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
               <p>Alſo you ſhall not buy any maner of ſuch Graine as we ſhal appoint you to ſel,<note place="margin">None to buy ſuch kinde of Corne as they ſhall bring to ſel, but by warrant vpon reaſonable cauſe.</note> from this day forwardes, but vpon very eſpeciall and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie cauſe to bee allowed by vs, vntill ſuch time as all and euery ſuch maner Graines as we at this time ſhall appoint you to ſell, be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our appointment and order by you ſolde. And if you ſhall not ſowe ſo much this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:806:6"/> yeere as the Iurie hath preſented that yee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſowe, or if you nowe haue, or ſhall haue knowledge, or ſhall geſſe hereafter at any time, either by threſhing of the Mowe or Shocks or otherwiſe, that yee haue more ſtore of any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Graine, then the Iurie hath preſented vnto vs: that then ye ſhal forth with vpon ſuch knowledge thereof had, make true relation thereof vnto vs, or vnto two of vs both what portion of your ſeede Corne ſhalbe left vnſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what further quantity you ſhall perceiue you haue, then was at the firſt preſented.</p>
               <p>That ſo ſoone as you perceiue you ſpend not after the rate of ſo much Corne as wee haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto you for the finding of your houſe, yee ſhall make true report vnto vs or two of vs, how much leſſe ye ſpend.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">No corne to be bought for to ſell againe.</note>Yee ſhall buy no Corne to ſell it againe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall you by any colour directly or indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, appoint any your ſeruants, or any other perſon to be a Badger of your Corn, other then to carry your Corne to the Market there to bee ſolde as your owne, without changing of any propertie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">No Corn to be bought but in open Market.</note>Yee ſhall neither buy nor ſell any maner of corne, but in the open Market, vnleſſe the ſame bee to ſome poore handicraftes men, or day la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers within the Pariſh wherein you doe dwell, that cannot conueniently come to the market Townes, by reaſon of diſtance of place, according to ſuch direction as ſhalbe giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you in that behalfe by vs the Iuſtices of the Peace of that Diuiſion, within which you doe dwell, or two of vs, and to none of theſe aboue
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:806:6"/> one buſhel at a time, and thereof you ſhal keepe or cauſe to be kept a particular note in writing to whom you ſhall ſo ſell weekely, and at what prices, ſo as the ſame may appeare to the Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be done without fraud or abuſe.</p>
               <p>That the Iuſtices of the Peace within their ſeuerall Diuiſions haue ſpeciall regard that Ingroſſers of Corne be carefully ſeene vnto,<note place="margin">Inquirie to be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſers.</note> and inquiſitions to be made for knowledge of them, ſo as they may be ſeuerely puniſhed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the law: And where ſuch are found, to make Certificates of their names and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and of the proofes to the Queenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Atturney generall for the time being, who is directed ſpeedily to informe againſt them for the ſame, and to ſee that none be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to buy any Corne to ſell againe, but by ſpeciall licence, and that of all maner of licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by Iuſtices of the Peace or by any other au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, the parties that ſhall haue ſuch licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhal cauſe an entry to be made in the books of the Peace remaining with the <hi>Cuſtos Rotu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum,</hi> or the Clerke of the Peace,<note place="margin">An order for all licences from the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the Peace, to bee kept in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord.</note> for entrie wherof the party ſhal not pay aboue two pence, and thereof the <hi>Cuſtos Rotulorum,</hi> or the Clerke ſhall keepe a good Regiſter to be ſhewed to the Iuſtices, whenſoeuer they ſhall require the ſight thereof.</p>
               <p>That they take order with the common Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers for the baking of Rie, Barley, Peaſe,<note place="margin">Regard to the Bakers for keeping of the ſiſe of bread.</note> and Beanes for the vſe of the poore, and that they appoint ſpeciall and fit perſons diligently to ſee the people well dealt withall by the common Bakers and Brewers in all Townes and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:806:7"/> in their Weights and Aſſizes, hauing alſo regard, that the Deputies of the Clerke of the Market do not abuſe themſelues in vnlawfull exactions for Weight and Meaſure, and effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to inquire for and ſearch out the default therein, and therupon to giue order for puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the offendor ſeuerely,<note place="margin">Bread faultie in any exceſſe to be ſold to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of the poore.</note> according to the Law: and where any notable exceſſiue offence ſhalbe in the Bakers, to cauſe the bread to bee ſolde to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poorer ſort vnder the ordinary prices, as in part of puniſhment of the Baker.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">No Badger to buy Corne but in open Market, and with ſufficient licence in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note>That no Badgers of corn, Bakers or Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers buy any Graine, or commune or bargaine for the ſame, but in the time of open Markets, and that but by Licence vnder the hands of the Iuſtices of the Diuiſion where they doe dwell, or three of them, and that they weekely bring their Licence with them to the Market where they do either buy or ſel, or els not to be ſuffered to buy any: And that the Licence containe how much Graine, of what kinde, &amp; for what place they are licenced to buy and cary, that there be ſet down vpon the Licence in writing, the day, place, quantitie, and price at which the Corne is bought, that they take but meaſurably for the cariage, baking, and brewing thereof, that they ſhewe their bookes weekely to ſuch as the Iuſtices of the Diuiſion wherein they dwell,<note place="margin">The Bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to ſhew weekly their bookes of buying.</note> ſhall appoint for that purpoſe being no Bakers or Badgers of Corne, and that thoſe within euery xiiii. dayes make report to the Iuſtices of the Diuiſion wherein they dwell, howe the people are dealt withall by the Badgers, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, and Brewers, and that ſuch as haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:806:7"/> to liue on, or that are knowen to bee of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny common euill behauiur, bee not permitted to bee Badgers of Corne, of which ſort com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the report is that there are too many, and therefore the ſame would be remedied and foreſeene: Alſo that no Badgers bee permitted but ſuch as the Statute doeth limite,<note place="margin">No Iuſtices ſeruant to be a Badger, nor none other, but ſuch as ſhal be licenſed in open Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> and that no ſeruant of any bee licenced to bee a Badger, except ſixe of the Iuſtices at the leaſt ſhall in open Seſſions for ſome neceſſary cauſe allow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch, and that none at all be allowed a Bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, except he be allowed in open ſeſſions, &amp; not to be, as it is in many places, abuſed for gaine of the Clerke of the Peace, or a Iuſtices Clerke graunted without allowance of the reſt of the Iuſtices in their open Seſſions.<note place="margin">No Badger, Baker, Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or Puruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to buy Graine, vntill an houre after the full Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket beginne.</note> And further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, that none be permitted to buy or prouide Corne in the Market in groſſe, as a Badger or Baker, Brewer, or Purueyour and ſuch like, vpon paine of impriſonment, vntill one houre or more after the full Market be begunne, that the poore may be firſt ſerued.</p>
               <p>That the ſaid Iuſtices, or two,<note place="margin">Some Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the Market, to ſee the poore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued vpon reaſonable prices.</note> or one of them at the leaſt in euery Diuiſion, ſhall be perſonal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly preſent at euery market within their ſeueral Diuiſions, during the whole time of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, to ſee the orders to be taken by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hereof to be wel obſerued, and the poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple prouided of neceſſary Corne, and that with as much fauour in the prices, as by their ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt perſwaſion of the Iuſtices can be obtained. By this it is not meant to charge any Lorde of Parliament being a Iuſtice of Peace, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende vpon any ſuch ſeruice in any Market,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:806:8"/> otherwiſe then it ſhall be with his owne good will: but in all other cauſes tending to the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of theſe orders, it is hoped that euery perſon of any eſtate, will readily giue aduiſe and aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Where Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices are wanting in any Hundred, for to appoint ſome rich per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to ſupply the want.</note>If there ſhall be any Hundred, Rape, or Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentake within the ſayd Countie, within the which or nere thereunto no ſufficient number of the ſayd Iuſtices of the Peace do dwell or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit, the ſayd Shirife and foure Iuſtices of the Peace of that Countie, ſhall in that caſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt ſome other honeſt Gentleman, or the high Conſtables vnder Conſtables, or ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, graue, honeſt, and ſubſtantiall perſons, not being Corne maſters, dwelling within the ſaid Hundred, Rape or Wapentake, as they ſhal by their diſcretions thinke conuenient, to haue the charge, doing the execution of theſe orders there: whom they ſhal alſo inſtruct how to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the ſame diligently and vprightly.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">That mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers exhort the richer ſort to be libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to helpe the poore with mony or vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual needful.</note>That all good meanes and perſwaſions be vſed by the Iuſtices in their ſeuerall diuiſions, and by admonitions and exhortations in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in the Churches, by the Preachers and Miniſters of the Word, that the poore may be ſerued of Corne at conuenient and charitable prices. And to the furtherance thereof, that the richer ſort be earneſtly mooued by Chriſtian charitie, to cauſe their Graine to be ſolde vnder the common prices of the Market to the poorer ſort: A deed of mercy, that will doubtleſſe be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded of Almightie God.</p>
               <p>That there be no buying or bargeining of any kinde of Corne but in open Market, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:806:8"/> that the Iuſtices in their ſeueral Diuiſions, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine common Maulſters of making Barlie Mault,<note place="margin">To make Mault of otes in countreys where there hath bene vſe thereof.</note> in thoſe countreyes and places where there be Oates ſufficient to make Mault of for the vſe of the people, and to reſtraine as well the brewing of Barley Mault, by or for Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes or common Tiplers in thoſe Countreis and places, as alſo the exceſſe vſe of any kinde of Mault, by al common Brewers, Maulſters, and common Tiplers, according to the true meaning of this Article: And that the vnneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary number of Alehouſes and common Tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers be foorth with ſuppreſſed in all places, and that direction bee giuen to all Tipling houſes, Tauernes and Alehouſes, not to ſuffer any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to repaire thither to eate and drinke at vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable times, or to continue in ſuch houſes longer, then to ſatiſfie their neceſſitie of eating and drinking.</p>
               <p>That the Iuſtices vſe al other good meanes poſſible that are not mentioned in theſe orders,<note place="margin">No waſt of bread Corne ſuperfluouſly, nor any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe thereof but for ſeeding of people.</note> that the Markets may be well ſerued, and the poore relieued in their prouiſions during this time of dearth. And that no expenſe of any Graine meet for bread to feede men, be waſted vpon feeding of dogges or other beaſtes, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that any bee ſpent in making ſtuffe called Starche,<note place="margin">None ſuffered to make Starch of any Graine.</note> as of late there hath bene diſcouered great quantity expended in that vaine mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, being in no ſort to be ſuffered to continue, the rather alſo for that there are other things not hurtfull to the foode of man, that may ſerue for ſuch purpoſes, if ſuch purpoſes at leaſt were requiſite.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:806:9"/>
               <p>be ſolde either in Corne or meale, but to charge them to continue the orderly vſe of grinding of all maner of Corne that ſhalbe brought to them, in reaſonable good ſort, and vpon reaſonable Tolle. And for better performance hereof ſome of the Iuſtices not affectionated to the Millers, ſhall ſome time perſonally themſelu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s reſort to the milles to ouerſee the doings of the ſaid Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and compell them to doe their dueties. And where none of the Iuſtices can as need ſhall be, weekely looke thereto perſonally, they ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point certaine honeſt perſons weekely to attend therto, and to enforme themſelues of the poorer ſort, how they are vſed in this time of dearth, for their grinding and their Toll, and preſent the defaults to the Iuſtices, to be ſpeedily reformed with all due ſeueritie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Conferences to be had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Peace in the Shires, and the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall officers of Cities and townes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions of Graine, for the inhabitants in Cities and corporate Townes.</note>Item, where there are within the circuite of any Shire, or thereto adioyning any Cities that are incorporated as Townes within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or any other Townes incorporate, that haue by good authoritie Iuſtices of Peace of their owne inhabitants, for that commonly ſuch Cities and Townes haue their greateſt number of houſholders that are no owners of graine, but haue common Bakers, &amp; Brewers, muſt of neceſſitie buy &amp; prouide their Corne or Meale at the Markets neere thereto, to ſerue all other the inhabitants and reſiants within the ſaid Cities and Townes: For the prouiſion of all ſuch Cities &amp; Townes, it ſhalbe neceſſary that the Iuſtices of the Peace of the Shires next to the ſame Cities and Townes ſhall haue a meeting and conference with the head Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the ſayd Cities and Townes, howe and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:806:9"/> in what good manner the Bakers and Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and other houſholders that ſhall alſo haue neede to prouide Corne or Meale for the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie vſe of the priuate houſholdes, may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided at the Markets neere to the ſame. And after due conference had hereof, there ſhall bee by the Iuſtices of Peace, and the foreſaide head Officers ſome good orders ſet downe, ſuch as both may ſerue for the needefull vſe of the ſame Townes and Cities, and alſo may not by abuſe giue cauſe of raiſing of prices in the Markets &amp; Countries adioyning. And where there ſhall be adioyning to the ſame Cities &amp; Townes, or not farre diſtant, diuers Shires, (as in many places ſuch is the ſituation of them) there ſome of the Iuſtices of euery Shire ſo adioyning, or not farre diſtant, ſhall vſe ſuch conference and take ſuch orders with the ſaide Officers, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is mentioned. And in ſuch caſes the Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of euery ſuch Shire ſhalbe enformed mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally from the one Shire vnto the other, of the needefull prouiſions to bee made from time to time for the ſaide Cities and Townes, ſo as euery Shire may proportionably yeelde reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſuccour and reliefe out of their Markets to the Purueyors or to the Bakers, &amp; Brewers as ſhall be requiſite without burthening of the one, more then the other may reaſonably beare. And if neede ſhall require, the aforeſaide princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Officers ſhall not refuſe to acquaint the Iuſtices, from whence the prouiſion ſhall bee bought and prouided, howe ſuch prouiſions ſo had and bought in Markets are ſpent, that by colour of ſuch prouiſions no abuſe be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:806:10"/> to encreaſe the prices, and ſo to leaue the poore vnable to be relieued.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces exempted from the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the Iuſtices of peace in the bodyes of the Shires.</note>If there bee any ſpeciall part within any Shire, that hath as a libertie by ſpeciall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions any Iuſtices of the Peace within the ſame, the Shirife of the Shire ſhall ſend vnto the principall owner or Officer of ſuch Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, notice of theſe orders, and ſhall charge them that the Iuſtices of the Peace within ſuch Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie doe their dueties for execution of al theſe orders, as farre foorth as ſhall be requiſite, and therein alſo to vſe by conference the aduiſe of ſome other Iuſtices next adioyning.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Regard to ſtay all tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Grayne out of the realme.</note>That in all Counties maritimme where Ports or Creeks are, by which any Corne may be carried out of the Realme, though alſo there are Commiſſioners appointed vnder the great Seale of England, to take care that no Corne be ſhipped or laden in any veſſell to paſſe out of the Realme: Yet neuertheleſſe, the Iuſtices of the Peace that are not placed in that Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, if they be no owners of Corne to ſell, ſhall alſo vſe their diligence to ſtay ſuch lading of Corne, either in Ports or Creekes, or vpon any Riuers leading to the ſame. And if the foreſaide Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners ſhall not do their dueties therein by authoritie of their commiſſion, then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iuſtice by authoritie of theſe orders ſhall make ſtay of all ſuch tranſportation, and in his ſo doing, ſhalbe allowed and maintained. And this is thought meet to be in this ſort directed, for that it may be doubted, that amongeſt ſo many as are appointed in the foreſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion againſt tranſportation, ſome may bee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:806:10"/> miſtaken, being themſelues either tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or friends or fauourers to tranſporters, or negligent in the execution of the charge com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them.</p>
               <p>That the Iuſtices of the Peace doe once eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moneth certifie their doings and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings by force of theſe inſtructions vnto the Sheriffe of the ſayde Countie,<note place="margin">Certificate to be made of the Execution of theſe Orders monethly to the Sheriffe, and he to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the ſame to the priuie Counſell with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in euery fourty dayes.</note> in which certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate they ſhall alſo make certificate of ſuch Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices as ſhall be abſent from any of theſe ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the true cauſe of their abſence, and ſhal alſo certifie the vſuall prices of all kindes of Graine in their markets for that moneth paſt: Of all which the ſame Sheriffe ſhall certifie to the Priuie counſell without any delay, ſo as he doe certifie once in euery fourtie dayes at the furtheſt, and ſo as alſo the default in any Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice that ſhalbe abſent without neceſſary cauſe,<note place="margin">To certifie what Iuſtices be abſent from the ſeruice, that ſuch as witho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t iuſt excuſe ſhall not attend, may be diſpla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and their roumes, if there be neede, ſupplied.</note> may be duely conſidered, and reformed by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of her Maieſties Counſell, as reaſon ſhall require: whereby ſuch perſons as are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as Iuſtices for their credite, may not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in thoſe roomes wherein they ſhall bee founde not diſpoſed to attende ſuch neceſſary and godly ſeruices as this is, but that others of better diſpoſition may ſupply thoſe roomes, if there ſhall bee neede of any ſuch number, as in moſt places it is thought not very neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the number of late yeeres beeing in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon opinion more hurtfull then profitable to Iuſtice.</p>
               <p>And if any ſhall offend againſt the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of theſe inſtructions, or of any part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or ſhall vſe any ſiniſter meane to the defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:806:11"/> thereof, that ſuch be ſeuerely puniſhed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Lawes: and for ſuch obſtinate perſons as ſhall not conforme themſelues, the Iuſtices ſhall at their pleaſure binde them to appeare before the Queenes Maieſties priuie Counſell by a day certaine, there to be further dealt with by ſeuere puniſhment, for the better enſample of all others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Articles annexed to the former <hi>Orders, to be executed by the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of Peace, in places where they ſhall thinke conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient. 1594.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, to take viewe of the number of Ale-houſes, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailing houſes, and tipling houſes in euery Towne, Pariſh, Village, and Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let within their Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and vpon view had, to conſider what number of them are neceſſary and fitte for euery Towne, Pariſh, Village, and Hamlet to continue: And thereupon to diſcharge the ſuperfluous num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and ſuch as are vnmeete to keepe the ſame, and to allowe a conuenient number, and no more.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They which ſhall be allowed, to be of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt conuerſation, &amp; that haue no other meanes to liue by, and to giue newe bandes to her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:806:11"/> vſe, to perfourme the orders following, and ſuch of them as refuſe to bee bound, not to be permitted to continue to keep any Alehouſe, Vitailing, or Tipling houſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To take ſtrait order with the Brewers, that they ſerue no Beere, or Ale to any Alehouſ-keeper, Victualler, or Tipler, but at ſuch Rate, and price, as by the Iuſtices of Peace ſhalbe ſet downe, and appoynted by authoritie of the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 23. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. And yet the ſame to bee well ſodden, and well brewed of wholeſome Graine, as it ought to be, vpon paine, &amp;c. to be impoſed by the Iuſtices.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That no Vitailers, Tiplers, and Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe-keepers haue in their houſes, or doe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to be brought into their houſes any Cards, Dice, or Tables, nor to ſuffer any to play in their houſes, yardes, or backſides at any Cards, Tables, Dice, or other vnlawfull games.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That no Vitailer, Tipler, or Ale-houſe-keeper ſhal dreſſe, or ſuffer to be dreſſed and eaten within his houſe, any fleſh vpon any forbidden day, ſauing for himſelfe and his ſeruaunts, in caſes of neceſſitie, according to the Statute in that behalfe prouided, and this to be parcell of the Condition of their Bond.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That no Vitailer, Tipler, or Ale-houſe-keeper ſhall permit, &amp; ſuffer any perſon, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to lodge in his houſe aboue a day &amp; a night, but ſuch as he wil anſwer for, as the Statutes yet in force doe require.</p>
               <p n="7">7. To giue ſtraight order and charge to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Conſtable, or other ſuperiour Officer, to whom it may appertaine, that euery of them
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:806:12"/> ſhall euery fifteene dayes ſearch, and enquire of the ſaid &amp; other like diſorders, as by the Lawes and Statutes of this Realme, they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and required. And if it ſhall ſeeme to the Iuſtices, that the petie Conſtable be either a Vitailer, or one that ſhall fauour the Vitai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in their faultes, ſome other meeter perſon to be appointed to make the ſayde Inquiſition and Certificate.</p>
               <p n="8">8 That Inquiſition bee made in what pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Mault is commonly made to bee ſolde, by ſuch as are called Maulſters, and who they be, and to take order, that by buying and Engroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of barley to make Mault, they do not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſtore vp greater quantitie of Mault, then they vſually bring to Markets, thereby to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end of the yeere to encreaſe the price thereof exceſſiuely, of which abuſe the Iuſtices are to take care to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:806:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
